so anyway that's what you were speaking
about today
yesterday sum
time how to practice
sum have to calm down in regards the
breath the well especially cuz we we
talk as I said we talk a lot about the
right endurance and sense restraint and
every gradual um every description of
the gradual training in the sutas starts
starts with that so you won't be doing
proper Samar unless you fully
restrained uh curbed and and
self-controlled so that is a like seeing
the danger in The sl's Fault then not
following things with eyes ears nose and
so on and eating in moderation exactly
and then that leads to the kind of
watchfulness and then some and on so but
it might create an impression that okay
so it's just about endurance endurance a
lot it's about endurance but then there
is a point where you can calm calm
within the endurance calm yourself
within the endurance so then end the
same endurance is not
unpleasant that that patient endurance
as the foremost austerity it does not
need to be felt unpleasantly
and that's the that's the difference in
the um in the sutas when he talks about the
um in the sutas when he talks about the
um like makana his way to Enlightenment
was quick and pleasant as in it didn't
take long because he was the master of
of of the right samtha the right caling
so although he went through the same
process of you know abandoning kesa and
everything else that would make people
go mad for him he didn't feel any
displeasure because his mind was so so
un unshakable
sarut on the other hand the foremost in
wisdom after the Buddha he said his way
was long and
unpleasant so he had to endure more pain
that on account of that patient
endurance of course he still had some
and janas and so on and when he did he
became enlightened so the role of that
samata which often goes with
vasana is is obviously significant and
crucial in a way but as as as I was
always saying you can't meditate rightly
unless you have the right View
that statement can be a bit too abstract
for people so practically the reason why
you won't be meditating rightly without
a right view is because your meditation
your samata will not be calming of the
endurance it will be rooted in a version
towards endurance it will be rooted in
you trying to get rid of the discomfort
of endurance through this meditation
technique and means you're the endure
which means you're ignoring well you're
blocking the direction through which
some the woodwor calm you and make your
way to Enlightenment Pleasant make your
endurance Pleasant makes so endurance is
not negotiable how much you're going to
negotiable how much you're going to
suffer on account of it how much your
mind will be tormented yeah that depends
on an individual depending on your
faculties if you're more about like we
pass aside or if you're more about
calming down but it needs to be done
that's why again gradual way always
starts by CA seeing the danger in the
slightest fault full sens trained not
giving into sensuality acting out of
will will distraction moderation eating
results in watchfulness results in
buildup of endurance and now within that
you can learn what calmness is what true
samata is but not at expense or not like
oh I'll deal with endurance the pain of
it I'll deal with the discomfort I'll
manage it cuz for most people without a
Right View that's what meditation
is which means just becomes another
management another cover up that rooted
in aversion towards
discomfort and you're not appro in
anything so one is
enduring not giving into any
defilement and the pressure is
there pressuring pressuring pressuring
but you're not giving in you're not
giving in there you go that's your endurance
in there you go that's your endurance
then and again you have a pressure and
that's why it's pressure like but just
you know do this or do that in order to
get rid of the pressure so you see that
you feel that whatever you be doing
you'll be acting in order to get rid of
the pressure so while you're all full of
Doubt conflicted giving in or or
refusing to give in tempted pressured
enduring the pain what else is there
that you are kind of aware of and you
can be aware of and it's enduring and
you doing it and it doesn't require
effort and it doesn't require special
attention and it cannot become um
something you do in order to get rid of
this or that because it's just too
subtle of an action what is there
happening while you're all tormented
with the pressure you're not giving
in breathing in breathing out that's
what's happening so that's why it's the the
happening so that's why it's the the
anapanasati whenever the word describ
it's like he knows like knowingly he
breathes in knowingly so it's about the
knowledge of your breath that it's
already there happening to the body so
to speak so that's what we speak that's
what we say like um the uh the
peripheral so it's not like okay so you
might you might even like you know if
you're all wound up through that
endurance and sens is pressuring you and
so on you might feel like okay so I'll
breathing like this I'll breathing like
yeah whatever do it but at the same time
just know that you can only do that
because the breath is already there
breathing so it's effortless it's a that's why
so it's effortless it's a that's why
it's a neutral action it's a action that
cannot truly if you see it in that
peripheral sense through like if you
just know it not necessarily do it
because you don't need to do it in order
to breathe you're already breathing
while you're trying to do all these
other things including enduring getting
rid of the endurance and so on so that's
why oh all I need to do I don't need to
do this in order for it to be the action
that will calm me down all I need to do
is know it happening underneath whatever
is going on here mindfulness of reading
cuz it's underneath
already so that's what means put it
first put it before whatever else you're
occupied with not in response to not at
the expense of and so on and even now
while we are
talking breathing is there and you can
know even while you're talking that
you're still breathing in breathing out
you don't need to control it you need to
stop it I don't need toop am I breathing
I know I'm breathing however vaguely
there is still the thread of the
knowledge of the same breath breathing
in breathing out so it's that thread of
that peripheral knowledge that doesn't
require any action just pure
recognition that's how you start to
practice anapanasati in the right
direction as a just something you're
aware of that's there you're not doing
it in response to this it's there
happening and you just choose to not
forget it that's it within this pressure
or whatever else and if you cultivate
sufficiently enough that not forgetting
of the bread recollected of the bread
mindfulness of the bread that's why it's
at it will come down any hindrance that
was there occupying you or pressuring
you he will take away that um uh first
person like engagement with this
pressure with this hindrance and I must
do this I must do this and it's just
things will be just seen for what they
are and during their neither Pleasant
nor unpleasant
neutral and then in itself would be very
pleasant obviously because you just
relieve yourself with pressure without
trying to get rid of
it and that's the true s and then like
oh yeah that's s you can do because you
have the right view now that prevents
you from trying to manage at any expense
that recognizes within the endurance I
need to find the calmness and that will
then Force you in the direction of what
true calmness
is so you know there's an in breath and
out breath an action that is within my
experience and pretty much fundamental
for any other action I do it precedes it
structurally so to speak like you know I
can stand up walk talk all of that
requires breathing to be there
and that's how you calm the Sankara the
the determination of the body through
calming the determination of the body
which is in and out of breath um all
your bodily actions will come down or
the pressure to bodily actions will come
down and there's a similar said
anapanasati when practiced made much of
you know when you become proficient in
it properly through that well through
that non-management but the direction of
calming of your pressure through it uh
it's like the rain they would sort of of
clean the air of all the dust
particles but you can't emphasize enough
that the the point that like if you're
doing it as a technique as a method as
something you're doing adhering focusing
hard in front of you you're doing it at
the expense of your container of
endurance that you have developed you're
doing it as a as an escape means you're
doing it because you you reverse towards
discomfort of it and that's why you're
doing it wrong that's why it's just the
extension of sensuality because what
what else is the principle of sensuality
is underlying tendency to aversion turns
you towards getting rid of it by the
means of anything that's not as averse
or more pleasant that's that's the
principle of centrality that's where
people go to censal desires and so on
and would have said that when when a a
ignorable mind is Touched by an
unpleasant feeling doesn't know any
other Escape doesn't know any other
calming in regard to the discomfort that
endures other than turning toward sensuality but
other than turning toward sensuality but
each time they turn to sensuality more
of the underlying tendency because of
which they were suffering on account of
the original discomfort will
increase and then the underlying
tendency for depending on more pleasure
will also increase so the more you give
in to the direction of trying to manage
get rid of your pain get rid of the
suffering through replacing it through
any more pleasant experience well the
worse it gets like scratching the
edch so that's the whole point of CA
sense restraint virtue
moderation watchfulness it's exactly
that to provide you
container they will not go to
centrality they will reveal and and
literally what you are what you're
averse to it's no one's fault it's the setup of
to it's no one's fault it's the setup of
the Aggregates the setup of the senses
they are
basically well they're not pleasant in
themselves let's put it that way having
a body is a chore having senses is it's
it's it's it's this resistance natural
resistance that you are paired with and
you have to endure whether you want it
or not so that's why like see you're not
born with all this like a newborn baby
doesn't have all this proliferate
sensuality but it has setup of the
senses that in themselves are pressuring
unpleasant resisting
resisting
ignorance ignorant mind and that means
automatic direction toward its pleasure
avoiding this and that's that's the word
would refer to the newborn baby St has
the same underlying Tendencies that's
why it will become the mind that
dependent on sensuality that that
doesn't want pain so so your um patient
endurance your SE somebody is about
to containing you trying to spill out to
Avid Senses at the expense of the senses
that are kind of unendurable or so it
feels and by the way that's also why ill
will is paired with it you are already
averse towards your own sense
basis neutrality is the aversion because
they are
unpleasant if you don't endure that
aversion if you don't calm yourself in
regard to the aversion of your own
senses you go out there for pleasure
which means you will go out there for
any other kind of um that aversion will
proliferate with you with you going out
there with the pleasure so people have
ill will towards other people because
fundamentally they carry will towards
their own senses that's the root of
every will and because of the aversion towards
will and because of the aversion towards
their own senses they are dependent on
sensuality through other people in the
world it's the same
route so you approve that route of
aversion towards your own senses and uh
you have lost any sensal desire or any
will towards anywhere anywhere in the
world that doesn't make the senses
comfortable no no no just makes your
mind go beyond the this that basic
discomfort of the senses that you never
ever addressed cuz from the moment you
were born you your mind was going in the
direction of the world to avoid again
that's why people fear
boredom boredom just brings back that
which you've been out running from the
day one the discomfort of your senses that
one the discomfort of your senses that
are truly
uncomfortable so samata is when you stop
giving in blindly and holding views that
are about management of that
discomfort some is calming of that
discomfort after you have endured it
sufficiently enough and develop Clarity
in regard to it so calming the
discomfort within the how do you calm it
well any any saatana would calm it but
it might be too abstract like you know
ah my body is here or something too much
activity of breath that it's there all
the time from the day one as well and it
kind of precedes the senses it doesn't
require your senses in order to
breathe so if you cultivate make much of
your breath as calming of the endurance that
breath as calming of the endurance that
it's not negotiable that's our hardship
in half a night 7 Days Fortnight 7
months or 7 years at
most because the only reason you still
depend on on you know sensuality
distraction so on is because you're
still unable to endure the core of the
problem which is the census and that's
why Arun in the sutas who becomes a
awakened he says oh I've done all the
work there's absolutely no more
resistance no more last anything world
no more conceed nothing left any
disturbance that's left for me is just
on account of this six sense body that's
left Until It Breaks apart and that's a
no disturbance
anymore see cuz you're not actually the
senses are kind of uncomfortable but
they're not daoka in themselves it's
your resistance aversion to discomfort
on the deepest level of me cuz that's
the root of the problem this here is
uncomfortable and automatically that
discomfort means a version for
me
so it's not like must get rid of the
senses I must kill this body I no well
you're just going to send yourself to
who knows what other
body you know it's it's it's a good
opportunity to actually just train in
regard to discomfort of the
senses and not being averse towards it
through discovering calmness within it
CU there is like eye of the
stone but it takes effort you need to
develop it and when you do all of the
all of the fats that depend on on the
world gone mind is unmoved cuz that's what was
gone mind is unmoved cuz that's what was
moving the mind the aversion towards
this thing that I don't want nothing
else everything else was
secondary you know all the wrong views
and all the centrality it was all
secondary rooted in this
so that's the
um the correct SU